<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Home on Hugo-HT</title><link>https://hellenshengfy.github.io/</link><description>Recent content in Home on Hugo-HT</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Thu, 27 Apr 2023 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://hellenshengfy.github.io/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>On the birth of culture-historical archaeology</title><link>https://hellenshengfy.github.io/en/2023/04/27/essay-on-a-history-of-archaeological-thoughts/</link><pubDate>Thu, 27 Apr 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://hellenshengfy.github.io/en/2023/04/27/essay-on-a-history-of-archaeological-thoughts/</guid><description>The following is my essay for a class instructed by professor Yan Pan in Fudan University. The class is based on A History of Archaeological Thoughts by Bruce G.Trigger.
Hellen Sheng
Professor Yan Pan
A History of Archaeological Thoughts
April 27, 2023
On the birth of culture-historical archaeology The dramatic social transformation in the late nineteen centuries catalyzed the evolution and variation of archaeology ideology. Culture-historical archaeology became undoubtedly the most important method and theory among all.</description></item><item><title>My artifact drawings</title><link>https://hellenshengfy.github.io/en/2023/04/15/drawing/</link><pubDate>Sat, 15 Apr 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://hellenshengfy.github.io/en/2023/04/15/drawing/</guid><description>I audited artifact drawing class instructed by Ms Dong Weimiao in Fudan University. Here are some of my sketches.
Geometric Shape Rostrum Classroom Human Skeleton Ceramic Cup</description></item><item><title>Anth 207x: Why bipedality?</title><link>https://hellenshengfy.github.io/en/2023/04/10/anth-207x/</link><pubDate>Mon, 10 Apr 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://hellenshengfy.github.io/en/2023/04/10/anth-207x/</guid><description>I really like the edX course Anth 207x: Introduction to Human Evolution lectured by Professor Adam Van Arsdale of Wellesley College, and I took a series of notes to this course. This article is based on my notes.
Why we are bipedal creatures? There are various hypothesis:
Temperature: The environment in East African is hot and relatively dry, and it&amp;rsquo;s easier for a bipedal to stay cool during the day.</description></item><item><title>Anth 207x: How to know when was the LCA?</title><link>https://hellenshengfy.github.io/en/2023/03/23/anth-207x/</link><pubDate>Thu, 23 Mar 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://hellenshengfy.github.io/en/2023/03/23/anth-207x/</guid><description>I really like the edX course Anth 207x: Introduction to Human Evolution lectured by Professor Adam Van Arsdale of Wellesley College, and I took a series of notes to this course. This article is based on my notes.
As we talked before that chimps and human being evolve from common ancestor, but who can we know when latest common ancestor (LCA) lived?
The answer lies in the molecular clock. In 1960s, geneticists found that differences in some protein structures were accumulating at a near constant rate through time, which made the time estimation of LCA possible.</description></item><item><title>How does bipedality influence our skeleton: tibia, pelvis and others_Osteology (4)</title><link>https://hellenshengfy.github.io/en/2023/03/20/osteology/</link><pubDate>Mon, 20 Mar 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://hellenshengfy.github.io/en/2023/03/20/osteology/</guid><description>As I find osteology extremely interesting, I decide to write a special series for osteology based on my notes of Anth 207x: Introduction to Human Evolution lectured by Professor Adam Van Arsdale of Wellesley College.
Less curved tibia Compared with the chimpanzee tibia, huamn tibia is less curved and less flexed. This is because we human beings exclusively load our tibia from an anterior/posterior direction but chimps knuckwalk quadrupedally. Chimps do a lot of different activities where tibia get involved like climing the tree.</description></item><item><title>Anth 207x: Dating method</title><link>https://hellenshengfy.github.io/en/2023/03/15/dating-method/</link><pubDate>Wed, 15 Mar 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://hellenshengfy.github.io/en/2023/03/15/dating-method/</guid><description>I really like the edX course Anth 207x: Introduction to Human Evolution lectured by Professor Adam Van Arsdale of Wellesley College, and I took a series of notes to this course. This article is based on my notes.
Relative dating method 1.Geo-chronology: Correlate the age of different sedimentary layers across locations, particularly distinctive sedimentary layers like volcanic ash falls
2.Bio-chronolog: identify sequences based on fossils contained within these layers. For example, specific fossils are found across different locations.</description></item><item><title>How does bipedality influence our skeleton: femur_Osteology(3)</title><link>https://hellenshengfy.github.io/en/2023/03/10/osteology/</link><pubDate>Fri, 10 Mar 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://hellenshengfy.github.io/en/2023/03/10/osteology/</guid><description>As I find osteology extremely interesting, I decide to write a special series for osteology based on my notes of Anth 207x: Introduction to Human Evolution lectured by Professor Adam Van Arsdale of Wellesley College.
Being bipedality is a tremendous shift. It involves changes of entire skeleton:
Femur: 1. Bicondylar angle Being bipedal means we walk on one leg for every step and this means great weight and pressure on our legs.</description></item><item><title>Anth 207x: Miocene: the age of apes</title><link>https://hellenshengfy.github.io/en/2023/03/06/anth-207x/</link><pubDate>Mon, 06 Mar 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://hellenshengfy.github.io/en/2023/03/06/anth-207x/</guid><description>Miocene (a period between 22 million years ago and 5 million years ago) is sometimes known as &amp;ldquo;The Age of Apes&amp;rdquo;. A great diversity of apes lived on various continents of our planet during Miocene and the environment and the climate of the world was quite different from today.
During Miocene, the Mediterranean Sea used to be an open corridor of ocean during instead of a closed body of water. It thus connected the Atlantic Ocean and the Indian Ocean, allowing tropical forests to grow throughout Eurasia, not limited to tropical regions.</description></item><item><title>Anth 207x: Is evolution directional?</title><link>https://hellenshengfy.github.io/en/2023/03/03/anth-207xis-evolution-directional/</link><pubDate>Fri, 03 Mar 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://hellenshengfy.github.io/en/2023/03/03/anth-207xis-evolution-directional/</guid><description>I really like the edX course Anth 207x: Introduction to Human Evolution lectured by Professor Adam Van Arsdale of Wellesley College, and I took a series of notes to this course. This article is based on my notes.
My understanding of evolution: Lego though holes By definition, evolution is “the heritable changes in a population through time”. It seems like that evolution has a direction (for example: from simple to complex), but it is NOT the case.</description></item><item><title>How eating habit impacts skull_osteology (2)</title><link>https://hellenshengfy.github.io/en/2023/02/21/osteology/</link><pubDate>Tue, 21 Feb 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://hellenshengfy.github.io/en/2023/02/21/osteology/</guid><description>As I find osteology extremely interesting, I decide to write a special series for osteology based on my notes of Anth 207x: Introduction to Human Evolution lectured by Professor Adam Van Arsdale of Wellesley College.
I mentioned strong canine in primates in my last blog, so what a strong canine can lead to? Actually, it will exert great influence on the structure of canium.
Prominent snout. Roots of canines extend up into the rostrum resulting in more prominent snout on the skull.</description></item><item><title>Eating habit: canine and honing complex_osteology (1)</title><link>https://hellenshengfy.github.io/en/2023/02/20/osteology/</link><pubDate>Mon, 20 Feb 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://hellenshengfy.github.io/en/2023/02/20/osteology/</guid><description>As I find osteology extremely interesting, I decide to write a special series for osteology based on my notes of Anth 207x: Introduction to Human Evolution lectured by Professor Adam Van Arsdale of Wellesley College.
In order to eat raw meat, apes developed strong canians together with a honing complex. Honing complex is a complex that (1) the lower canines project into the diastema between the upper canine and the lateral incisor and (2) the upper canine projects into the diastema between the lower canine and the lower third premolar.</description></item><item><title>Markdown 试水</title><link>https://hellenshengfy.github.io/cn/2021/01/07/first-post-cn/</link><pubDate>Thu, 07 Jan 2021 13:42:27 -0500</pubDate><guid>https://hellenshengfy.github.io/cn/2021/01/07/first-post-cn/</guid><description>如果好奇以下的内容是如何实现的，请参考本页源代码 。
第一级标题 第二级标题 第三级标题 第四级标题 第五级标题 第六级标题 列表 Water Water Water Water Water Water Water Water Water Water Water Water 表格 Water Water Water Water Water Water Water Water1 Water Water Water Water 引语 知之为知之，不知为不知，是知也2。 — 孔子
数学公式 最简单的如，$1 + 1 = 3$</description></item><item><title>Markdown Testing</title><link>https://hellenshengfy.github.io/en/2021/01/07/second-post/</link><pubDate>Thu, 07 Jan 2021 13:37:57 -0500</pubDate><guid>https://hellenshengfy.github.io/en/2021/01/07/second-post/</guid><description>See the source code of this page if you are interested.
H1 H2 H3 H4 H5 H6 List Water Water Water Water Water Water Water Water Water Water Water Water Table Water Water Water Water Water Water Water Water1 Water Water Water Water Quotes What I cannot create, I do not understand2.</description></item><item><title>Misunderstandings: chimps are our ancestors/ our ancestors look like chimps</title><link>https://hellenshengfy.github.io/en/2020/05/19/misunderstandings/</link><pubDate>Tue, 19 May 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://hellenshengfy.github.io/en/2020/05/19/misunderstandings/</guid><description>Thanks to Darwin’s theory of evolution, now we know the fact that human beings are not created by god. However, many people hold the view that (1) chimps are our ancestors and (2) our ancestors look like chimps. These are misunderstandings.
Firstly, as what I wrote in my 2020-01-07 blog, Pan is the sister clay to Homos. Roughly 7 million years ago, chimps and human beings split from evolutionary tree and evolved in their own directions.</description></item><item><title>Hominids, Hominioid, Hominines, Hominins: What’s the difference?</title><link>https://hellenshengfy.github.io/en/2020/01/07/second-post/</link><pubDate>Tue, 07 Jan 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://hellenshengfy.github.io/en/2020/01/07/second-post/</guid><description>Hominids, Hominioid, Hominines and Hominins? When I first come up with these terms, I was quite confused and found it hard to distinguish one from the other. After reading the paper Human Evolution: Taxonomy and Paleobiology, I decide to write this article and introduce you these terms under new taxonomic classification system which based on molecular evidence.
First of all, let me show you the chart, to make things easier. This chart is drawn based on the taxonomy table illustrated in Human Evolution: Taxonomy and Paleobiology.</description></item><item><title>背影</title><link>https://hellenshengfy.github.io/cn/1925/10/01/beiying/</link><pubDate>Thu, 01 Oct 1925 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://hellenshengfy.github.io/cn/1925/10/01/beiying/</guid><description>我与父亲不相见已二年余了，我最不能忘记的是他的背影。那年冬天，祖母死了，父亲的差使也交卸了，正是祸不单行的日子，我从北京到徐州，打算跟着父亲奔丧回家。到徐州见着父亲，看见满院狼藉的东西，又想起祖母，不禁簌簌地流下眼泪。父亲说，“事已如此，不必难过，好在天无绝人之路！”
　回家变卖典质，父亲还了亏空；又借钱办了丧事。这些日子，家中光景很是惨淡，一半为了丧事，一半为了父亲赋闲。丧事完毕，父亲要到南京谋事，我也要回北京念书，我们便同行。
　到南京时，有朋友约去游逛，勾留了一日；第二日上午便须渡江到浦口，下午上车北去。父亲因为事忙，本已说定不送我，叫旅馆里一个熟识的茶房陪我同去。他再三嘱咐茶房，甚是仔细。但他终于不放心，怕茶房不妥帖；颇踌躇了一会。其实我那年已二十岁，北京已来往过两三次，是没有甚么要紧的了。他踌躇了一会，终于决定还是自己送我去。我两三回劝他不必去；他只说，“不要紧，他们去不好！”
　我们过了江，进了车站。我买票，他忙着照看行李。行李太多了，得向脚夫行些小费，才可过去。他便又忙着和他们讲价钱。我那时真是聪明过分，总觉他说话不大漂亮，非自己插嘴不可。但他终于讲定了价钱；就送我上车。他给我拣定了靠车门的一张椅子；我将他给我做的紫毛大衣铺好坐位。他嘱我路上小心，夜里警醒些，不要受凉。又嘱托茶房好好照应我。我心里暗笑他的迂；他们只认得钱，托他们直是白托！而且我这样大年纪的人，难道还不能料理自己么？唉，我现在想想，那时真是太聪明了！
　我说道，“爸爸，你走吧。”他望车外看了看，说，“我买几个橘子去。你就在此地，不要走动。”我看那边月台的栅栏外有几个卖东西的等着顾客。走到那边月台，须穿过铁道，须跳下去又爬上去。父亲是一个胖子，走过去自然要费事些。我本来要去的，他不肯，只好让他去。我看见他戴着黑布小帽，穿着黑布大马褂，深青布棉袍，蹒跚地走到铁道边，慢慢探身下去，尚不大难。可是他穿过铁道，要爬上那边月台，就不容易了。他用两手攀着上面，两脚再向上缩；他肥胖的身子向左微倾，显出努力的样子。这时我看见他的背影，我的泪很快地流下来了。我赶紧拭干了泪，怕他看见，也怕别人看见。我再向外看时，他已抱了朱红的橘子望回走了。过铁道时，他先将橘子散放在地上，自己慢慢爬下，再抱起橘子走。到这边时，我赶紧去搀他。他和我走到车上，将橘子一股脑儿放在我的皮大衣上。于是扑扑衣上的泥土，心里很轻松似的，过一会说，“我走了；到那边来信！”我望着他走出去。他走了几步，回过头看见我，说，“进去吧，里边没人。”等他的背影混入来来往往的人里，再找不着了，我便进来坐下，我的眼泪又来了。
　近几年来，父亲和我都是东奔西走，家中光景是一日不如一日。他少年出外谋生，独力支持，做了许多大事。那知老境却如此颓唐！他触目伤怀，自然情不能自已。情郁于中，自然要发之于外；家庭琐屑便往往触他之怒。他待我渐渐不同往日。但最近两年的不见，他终于忘却我的不好，只是惦记着我，惦记着我的儿子。我北来后，他写了一信给我，信中说道，“我身体平安，惟膀子疼痛利害，举箸提笔，诸多不便，大约大去之期不远矣。”我读到此处，在晶莹的泪光中，又看见那肥胖的，青布棉袍，黑布马褂的背影。唉！我不知何时再能与他相见！</description></item></channel></rss>