<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>English Posts on Hugo-HT</title><link>https://hellenshengfy.github.io/en/posts/</link><description>Recent content in English Posts on Hugo-HT</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Thu, 27 Apr 2023 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://hellenshengfy.github.io/en/posts/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>On the birth of culture-historical archaeology</title><link>https://hellenshengfy.github.io/en/2023/04/27/essay-on-a-history-of-archaeological-thoughts/</link><pubDate>Thu, 27 Apr 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://hellenshengfy.github.io/en/2023/04/27/essay-on-a-history-of-archaeological-thoughts/</guid><description>The following is my essay for a class instructed by professor Yan Pan in Fudan University. The class is based on A History of Archaeological Thoughts by Bruce G.Trigger.
Hellen Sheng
Professor Yan Pan
A History of Archaeological Thoughts
April 27, 2023
On the birth of culture-historical archaeology The dramatic social transformation in the late nineteen centuries catalyzed the evolution and variation of archaeology ideology. Culture-historical archaeology became undoubtedly the most important method and theory among all.</description></item><item><title>Anth 207x: Why bipedality?</title><link>https://hellenshengfy.github.io/en/2023/04/10/anth-207x/</link><pubDate>Mon, 10 Apr 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://hellenshengfy.github.io/en/2023/04/10/anth-207x/</guid><description>I really like the edX course Anth 207x: Introduction to Human Evolution lectured by Professor Adam Van Arsdale of Wellesley College, and I took a series of notes to this course. This article is based on my notes.
Why we are bipedal creatures? There are various hypothesis:
Temperature: The environment in East African is hot and relatively dry, and it&amp;rsquo;s easier for a bipedal to stay cool during the day.</description></item><item><title>Anth 207x: How to know when was the LCA?</title><link>https://hellenshengfy.github.io/en/2023/03/23/anth-207x/</link><pubDate>Thu, 23 Mar 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://hellenshengfy.github.io/en/2023/03/23/anth-207x/</guid><description>I really like the edX course Anth 207x: Introduction to Human Evolution lectured by Professor Adam Van Arsdale of Wellesley College, and I took a series of notes to this course. This article is based on my notes.
As we talked before that chimps and human being evolve from common ancestor, but who can we know when latest common ancestor (LCA) lived?
The answer lies in the molecular clock. In 1960s, geneticists found that differences in some protein structures were accumulating at a near constant rate through time, which made the time estimation of LCA possible.</description></item><item><title>Anth 207x: Dating method</title><link>https://hellenshengfy.github.io/en/2023/03/15/dating-method/</link><pubDate>Wed, 15 Mar 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://hellenshengfy.github.io/en/2023/03/15/dating-method/</guid><description>I really like the edX course Anth 207x: Introduction to Human Evolution lectured by Professor Adam Van Arsdale of Wellesley College, and I took a series of notes to this course. This article is based on my notes.
Relative dating method 1.Geo-chronology: Correlate the age of different sedimentary layers across locations, particularly distinctive sedimentary layers like volcanic ash falls
2.Bio-chronolog: identify sequences based on fossils contained within these layers. For example, specific fossils are found across different locations.</description></item><item><title>Anth 207x: Miocene: the age of apes</title><link>https://hellenshengfy.github.io/en/2023/03/06/anth-207x/</link><pubDate>Mon, 06 Mar 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://hellenshengfy.github.io/en/2023/03/06/anth-207x/</guid><description>Miocene (a period between 22 million years ago and 5 million years ago) is sometimes known as &amp;ldquo;The Age of Apes&amp;rdquo;. A great diversity of apes lived on various continents of our planet during Miocene and the environment and the climate of the world was quite different from today.
During Miocene, the Mediterranean Sea used to be an open corridor of ocean during instead of a closed body of water. It thus connected the Atlantic Ocean and the Indian Ocean, allowing tropical forests to grow throughout Eurasia, not limited to tropical regions.</description></item><item><title>Anth 207x: Is evolution directional?</title><link>https://hellenshengfy.github.io/en/2023/03/03/anth-207xis-evolution-directional/</link><pubDate>Fri, 03 Mar 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://hellenshengfy.github.io/en/2023/03/03/anth-207xis-evolution-directional/</guid><description>I really like the edX course Anth 207x: Introduction to Human Evolution lectured by Professor Adam Van Arsdale of Wellesley College, and I took a series of notes to this course. This article is based on my notes.
My understanding of evolution: Lego though holes By definition, evolution is “the heritable changes in a population through time”. It seems like that evolution has a direction (for example: from simple to complex), but it is NOT the case.</description></item><item><title>Osteology(2): bipedality</title><link>https://hellenshengfy.github.io/en/2023/03/01/osteology/</link><pubDate>Wed, 01 Mar 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://hellenshengfy.github.io/en/2023/03/01/osteology/</guid><description>As I find osteology extremely interesting, so I made a special osteology series from my notes based on Anth 207x: Introduction to Human Evolution lectured by Professor Adam Van Arsdale of Wellesley College.
Why we are bipedal creatures? There are various hypothesis:
Temperature: The environment in East African is hot and relatively dry, and it&amp;rsquo;s easier for a bipedal to stay cool during the day. Because most of body parts are away from the ground, bipedal species suffer from less thermal radiation.</description></item><item><title>Eating habit: canine and honing complex_osteology (1)</title><link>https://hellenshengfy.github.io/en/2023/02/20/osteology/</link><pubDate>Mon, 20 Feb 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://hellenshengfy.github.io/en/2023/02/20/osteology/</guid><description>As I find osteology extremely interesting, so I made a special osteology series from my notes based on Anth 207x: Introduction to Human Evolution lectured by Professor Adam Van Arsdale of Wellesley College.
In order to eat raw meat, apes developed strong canians together with a honing complex. Honing complex is a complex that (1) the lower canines project into the diastema between the upper canine and the lateral incisor and (2) the upper canine projects into the diastema between the lower canine and the lower third premolar.</description></item><item><title>Markdown Testing</title><link>https://hellenshengfy.github.io/en/2021/01/07/second-post/</link><pubDate>Thu, 07 Jan 2021 13:37:57 -0500</pubDate><guid>https://hellenshengfy.github.io/en/2021/01/07/second-post/</guid><description>See the source code of this page if you are interested.
H1 H2 H3 H4 H5 H6 List Water Water Water Water Water Water Water Water Water Water Water Water Table Water Water Water Water Water Water Water Water1 Water Water Water Water Quotes What I cannot create, I do not understand2.</description></item><item><title>Misunderstandings: chimps are our ancestors/ our ancestors look like chimps</title><link>https://hellenshengfy.github.io/en/2020/05/19/misunderstandings/</link><pubDate>Tue, 19 May 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://hellenshengfy.github.io/en/2020/05/19/misunderstandings/</guid><description>Thanks to Darwin’s theory of evolution, now we know the fact that human beings are not created by god. However, many people hold the view that (1) chimps are our ancestors and (2) our ancestors look like chimps. These are misunderstandings.
Firstly, as what I wrote in my 2020-01-07 blog, Pan is the sister clay to Homos. Roughly 7 million years ago, chimps and human beings split from evolutionary tree and evolved in their own directions.</description></item><item><title>Hominids, Hominioid, Hominines, Hominins: What’s the difference?</title><link>https://hellenshengfy.github.io/en/2020/01/07/second-post/</link><pubDate>Tue, 07 Jan 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://hellenshengfy.github.io/en/2020/01/07/second-post/</guid><description>Hominids, Hominioid, Hominines and Hominins? When I first come up with these terms, I was quite confused and found it hard to distinguish one from the other. After reading the paper Human Evolution: Taxonomy and Paleobiology, I decide to write this article and introduce you these terms under new taxonomic classification system which based on molecular evidence.
First of all, let me show you the chart, to make things easier. This chart is drawn based on the taxonomy table illustrated in Human Evolution: Taxonomy and Paleobiology.</description></item></channel></rss>