<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>English Posts on Hugo-HT</title><link>https://hellenshengfy.github.io/en/posts/</link><description>Recent content in English Posts on Hugo-HT</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Mon, 10 Jul 2023 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://hellenshengfy.github.io/en/posts/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>The classifcation standard of pottery sherds from Zhangshan site</title><link>https://hellenshengfy.github.io/en/2023/07/10/sherds/</link><pubDate>Mon, 10 Jul 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://hellenshengfy.github.io/en/2023/07/10/sherds/</guid><description>I helped Dr. Li Wei (Fudan University) to process pottery sherds uneared from Zhangshan site (Maqiao culture, ~ 3700BP). We set the classification standard for sherds together.
PDF: The classifcation standard of pottery sherds from Zhangshan site_clay Classification Standard The fabric of pottery:
Tempered sand 夹砂陶
Porosity: - Coarse sand 粗砂 - Fine sand 细砂 Clay 泥质陶</description></item><item><title>How to draw archaeological map using ArcGIS 10.5</title><link>https://hellenshengfy.github.io/en/2023/07/05/cfa/</link><pubDate>Wed, 05 Jul 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://hellenshengfy.github.io/en/2023/07/05/cfa/</guid><description>My mannual book to draw archaeological map using ArcGIS 10.5 based on introductory course of Dr. Li Wei (Fudan University).
Step 1. Download DEM files from Geospatial Data Cloud
In order to illustrate prehistorical sites in Shanghai on the map, we need to download 5 datasets.
Step 2. Import all files into ArcMap (click “Add data” - select files needed)
Step 3.</description></item><item><title>A Brief Introduction on ZooMS</title><link>https://hellenshengfy.github.io/en/2023/06/21/cfa/</link><pubDate>Wed, 21 Jun 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://hellenshengfy.github.io/en/2023/06/21/cfa/</guid><description>I read several papers on ZooMs which are really promising and interesting. I write a summary according to papers I read and photos credit to A Primer for ZooMS Applications in Archaeology.
Terminology ZooMS: Zooarchaeology by mass spectrometry
PMF: Collagen peptide mass fingerprinting
MALDI-TOF MS: Matrix-assisted laser desorption/ionization time-of-flight mass spectrometry
COL1: Type I collagen
PTM: Posttranslational modification
Type I collagen (COL1) ZooMS can also be referred as COL1 for taxonomic identification.</description></item><item><title>Major figures mentioned by Bruce G. Trigger's Book</title><link>https://hellenshengfy.github.io/en/2023/06/15/trigger/</link><pubDate>Thu, 15 Jun 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://hellenshengfy.github.io/en/2023/06/15/trigger/</guid><description>My summary table of major figures of A History of Archaeological Thought (Bruce G. Trigger)
Summary Table Name Year Accomplishments Lu Dalin 1042-1090 Baogutu John Aubrey 1626-1697 Plan of Avebury in Monumenta Britannica Bernard de Montfaucon 1655-1741 Antiquity Explained and Represented in Diagrams William Stukeley 1687-1765 View of Avebury in Abury William Hamilton 1730-1803 British collector and envoy in Naples Johann Joachim Winckelmann  1717-1768 The History of the Art of Antiquity; Progression of styles in Greek art James Hutton 1726-1797 Uniformatarian view of geological history Wilhelm von Humboldt 1767-1835 Educational reform in Prussia William Buckland 1784-1856 Catastrophic view of geological history Sven Nilsson 1787-1883 Zoology, subsistence patterns Christian Jurgensen Thomsen 1788-1865 Three age system Jean-Francois Champollion 1790-1832 Egyptian scrits decipherment Charles R.</description></item><item><title> On the evolution of human society: Lewis Morgan, Elman Service, Kwang-chih Chang and Su Bingqi</title><link>https://hellenshengfy.github.io/en/2023/06/12/cfa/</link><pubDate>Mon, 12 Jun 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://hellenshengfy.github.io/en/2023/06/12/cfa/</guid><description>The evolution of social organization is mentioned for many times in the classes I attended this semester. So I decided to write an article to summerize and compare different theories on the topic.
Lewis Morgan Lewis Morgan brought up the idea of &amp;ldquo;Savagery-Barbarism-Civilization&amp;rdquo; stages in his Ancient Society.
Periods Divisions Conditions Savagery I. Lower Status of Savagery Infancy of the Human Race Savagery II.</description></item><item><title>Major figures mentioned by Bruce G. Trigger's Book</title><link>https://hellenshengfy.github.io/en/2023/06/12/trigger/</link><pubDate>Mon, 12 Jun 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://hellenshengfy.github.io/en/2023/06/12/trigger/</guid><description>My summary table of major figures of A History of Archaeological Thought (Bruce G. Trigger)
Summary Table Name Year Accomplishments Lu Dalin 1042-1090 Baogutu John Aubrey 1626-1697 Plan of Avebury in Monumenta Britannica Bernard de Montfaucon 1655-1741 Antiquity Explained and Represented in Diagrams William Stukeley 1687-1765 View of Avebury in Abury William Hamilton 1730-1803 British collector and envoy in Naples Johann Joachim Winckelmann  1717-1768 The History of the Art of Antiquity; Progression of styles in Greek art James Hutton 1726-1797 Uniformatarian view of geological history Wilhelm von Humboldt 1767-1835 Educational reform in Prussia William Buckland 1784-1856 Catastrophic view of geological history Sven Nilsson 1787-1883 Zoology, subsistence patterns Christian Jurgensen Thomsen 1788-1865 Three age system Jean-Francois Champollion 1790-1832 Egyptian scrits decipherment Charles R.</description></item><item><title>My thoughts on statistical analysis of "Pass the skeleton key…"</title><link>https://hellenshengfy.github.io/en/2023/06/10/issue/</link><pubDate>Sat, 10 Jun 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://hellenshengfy.github.io/en/2023/06/10/issue/</guid><description>I just read Pass the skeleton key… Animals in an early Copper Age inhumation burial from Pusztataskony–Ledence I, Hungary and find two statistical issues.
On page 85, a statistical table is presented: And the interpretation of the table goes like this:
Condescending attitudes toward hares slightly outnumber those showing sympathy causing a moderate positive skew in the distribution, a visual trend also expressed in the univariate statistics calculated for the 39 proverbs (Figure7.</description></item><item><title>Notes on A History of Sea Ice in the Canadian Arctic Archipelago Based on Postglacial Remains of the Bowhead Whale (Balaena mysticetus)</title><link>https://hellenshengfy.github.io/en/2023/06/10/problems/</link><pubDate>Sat, 10 Jun 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://hellenshengfy.github.io/en/2023/06/10/problems/</guid><description>This is my note on A History of Sea Ice in the Canadian Arctic Archipelago Based on Postglacial Remains of the Bowhead Whale (Balaena mysticetus) by S. DYKE, JAMES HOOPER and JAMES M. SAVELLE. Photos below are originally 15 figures from the paper, and I combined them into 4 master figures for better illustration.
The bowhead (Balaena mysticetus) is a marine mammal that lives in waters covered by seasnonal sea ice (preferable to 30%-50% cover) and migrates annually, making it a good proxy of floe edge oscillation.</description></item><item><title> How pollen evidence can help us to rebuild paleo-environment</title><link>https://hellenshengfy.github.io/en/2023/05/25/climate/</link><pubDate>Thu, 25 May 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://hellenshengfy.github.io/en/2023/05/25/climate/</guid><description>This week, I read the Fire and flood management of coastal swampen abled first rice paddy cultivation in east China (Linchao H. et al). I think this paper could be an excellent case study on how to use pollen evidence to rebuild paleo-environment.
What can we tell from this chart?
I edited the chart from the paper for better illustration Phases A and G : High frequencies of marine and brackish water diatoms and estuRINE NPMs - estuarine environments</description></item><item><title> Neolithic culture in China_a summary table based on settlement archaeology course</title><link>https://hellenshengfy.github.io/en/2023/05/22/yinxu/</link><pubDate>Mon, 22 May 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://hellenshengfy.github.io/en/2023/05/22/yinxu/</guid><description>Below is my translation and edited table based on materials from settlement archaeology course lectured by Dr. Liwei (Fudan University).
Flower with multi-layered petals theory
First level: Central Plain region
Strong central plain (bold red) Weak central plain (grey) Second level: Five cultural regions around
Strong adjacent region (bold orange) Third level: Many other cultural zones
Summary table</description></item><item><title>The domestication of Guinea Pig</title><link>https://hellenshengfy.github.io/en/2023/05/15/anth/</link><pubDate>Mon, 15 May 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://hellenshengfy.github.io/en/2023/05/15/anth/</guid><description>Following is my presentation on the zooarchaeology class lectured by Dr. Dong Ningning
Prelude A 1610s painting by Jan Brueghel the Elder, one of the earliest portraits of guinea pig in Europe.
Before being a pet Introduction of Guinea Pig Zooarchaeology Zooarchaeological evidence on the domestication of Guinea pigs
Click here for full PDF</description></item><item><title>Seminar: Çatalhöyük</title><link>https://hellenshengfy.github.io/en/2023/05/13/catalhoyok/</link><pubDate>Sat, 13 May 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://hellenshengfy.github.io/en/2023/05/13/catalhoyok/</guid><description>This is my preparation material for a seminar on Çatalhöyük. Photos credit to papers in the reference.
Location A 13 hectares tell site in Central Anatolia. There are mainly two mounds in the area, and 34 acre East mound dated back to Neolithic period (7 400-6200 cal. BCE).
Map from Pearson JA(2007) Archaeologists Year Name Zooarchaeological results on cattle 1960s James Mellaart Cattle constitutes 70% of the faunal assemblage which might be biased because of hand collection without sieves 1993 Ian Hodder Cattle constitute 20-25% of the faunal assemblage and there is no indication of domestication of cattle Life in Çatalhöyük Peak Population : 3500-8000</description></item><item><title>Tiesanlu,Guandimiao and Daxingzhuang: bone workshops during Anyang period (ca. 1250-1050 BCE) and the weakness of the Formality concept brought up by Wang (2022)</title><link>https://hellenshengfy.github.io/en/2023/05/12/yinxu/</link><pubDate>Fri, 12 May 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://hellenshengfy.github.io/en/2023/05/12/yinxu/</guid><description>Today, in the zooarchaeology class, we read an article about a bone factory in Tiesanlu during Anyang period (ca. 1250-1050 BCE), which is quite interesting. So I further read related articles about other bone factories discovered in the area and here is my thoughts.
First, let us have a look at the location of three sites: Tiesanlu (2), Guandimiao(1) and Daxingzhuang(3)
Edited photo from my note based on chart from Hou (2018) Products in these sites:</description></item><item><title> My isotope experiment</title><link>https://hellenshengfy.github.io/en/2023/05/11/isotope/</link><pubDate>Thu, 11 May 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://hellenshengfy.github.io/en/2023/05/11/isotope/</guid><description>A simple diary on my first isotope test
1. Preparation Lab clothes and cloves on
My sample：T2325 and T2320
2. Grinding To remove dirt on the surface of samples
3. Cleaning Clean samples with ultrasonic machine
4. Drying 5. Mix with diluted hydrochloric acid 6. Heated filtration 7. Samples before test (Collagen) 8. Put samples into the machine</description></item><item><title>Wrap-up: Ape and Huamn Anatomy</title><link>https://hellenshengfy.github.io/en/2023/05/10/anatomy/</link><pubDate>Wed, 10 May 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://hellenshengfy.github.io/en/2023/05/10/anatomy/</guid><description>All images credit to Anth 207x: Introduction to Human Evolution and my notes based on this course, if no special citation.
Chapter 0: Hominids, Hominioid, Hominines, Hominins: What’s the difference? Hominids, Hominioid, Hominines and Hominins? When I first come up with these terms, I was quite confused and found it hard to distinguish one from the other. After reading the paper Human Evolution: Taxonomy and Paleobiology, I decide to write this article and introduce you these terms under new taxonomic classification system which based on molecular evidence.</description></item><item><title>Hominids, Hominioid, Hominines, Hominins: What’s the difference?</title><link>https://hellenshengfy.github.io/en/2023/05/07/second-post/</link><pubDate>Sun, 07 May 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://hellenshengfy.github.io/en/2023/05/07/second-post/</guid><description>Hominids, Hominioid, Hominines and Hominins? When I first come up with these terms, I was quite confused and found it hard to distinguish one from the other. After reading the paper Human Evolution: Taxonomy and Paleobiology, I decide to write this article and introduce you these terms under new taxonomic classification system which based on molecular evidence.
First of all, let me show you the chart, to make things easier. This chart is drawn based on the taxonomy table illustrated in Human Evolution: Taxonomy and Paleobiology.</description></item><item><title> Phytoliths in the paleovegetation reconstruction</title><link>https://hellenshengfy.github.io/en/2023/05/02/phytolith/</link><pubDate>Tue, 02 May 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://hellenshengfy.github.io/en/2023/05/02/phytolith/</guid><description>Phytoliths is a good alternative to pollen in the paleovegetation reconstructions, especially in the conditions where pollen evidence is badly preserved. Archaeologists can distinguish different types of phytoliths according to their shapes. However, further anaylsis is confined by the fact that, in most cases, a specific shape of phytoliths does not correspond to a specific plant species. Therefore, the picture drawn by phytoliths could be quite vague.
Photo credit to handout of Prof.</description></item><item><title>Major climate events since late Pleistocene</title><link>https://hellenshengfy.github.io/en/2023/05/01/climate/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 May 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://hellenshengfy.github.io/en/2023/05/01/climate/</guid><description>Late pleistocene Oldest Dryas cooling (18000-14700BP)
Bolling-Allerod warming (14700-12700BP)
Younger Dryas cooling (12700-11700BP)
Holocene 8.2 Ka cooling (8400-8000BP) Most influential cooling event during Holocene with a scale that is half of YD event. In China, we have Xinglongwa and Jingtoushan culture by that time.
4.2 Ka drought (4200BP-2200BP) This drought might put an end to Chinese Longshan culture, old kingdom of Egypt and Akkadian Empire.</description></item><item><title>On the birth of culture-historical archaeology</title><link>https://hellenshengfy.github.io/en/2023/04/27/essay-on-a-history-of-archaeological-thoughts/</link><pubDate>Thu, 27 Apr 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://hellenshengfy.github.io/en/2023/04/27/essay-on-a-history-of-archaeological-thoughts/</guid><description>The following is my essay for a class instructed by professor Yan Pan in Fudan University. The class is based on A History of Archaeological Thoughts by Bruce G.Trigger.
Hellen Sheng
Professor Yan Pan
A History of Archaeological Thoughts
April 27, 2023
On the birth of culture-historical archaeology The dramatic social transformation in the late nineteenth century catalyzed the evolution and variation of archaeology ideology. Culture-historical archaeology became undoubtedly the most important method and theory among all.</description></item><item><title>My artifact drawings</title><link>https://hellenshengfy.github.io/en/2023/04/15/drawing/</link><pubDate>Sat, 15 Apr 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://hellenshengfy.github.io/en/2023/04/15/drawing/</guid><description>I audited artifact drawing class instructed by Dr.Dong Weimiao in Fudan University. Here are some of my sketches.
Geometric Shape Rostrum Classroom Tomb Human Skeleton Ceramic Cup</description></item><item><title> Amazing: zooarchaeology as circumstantial evidence of the origins of metallurgy</title><link>https://hellenshengfy.github.io/en/2023/04/11/catalhoyok/</link><pubDate>Tue, 11 Apr 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://hellenshengfy.github.io/en/2023/04/11/catalhoyok/</guid><description>All photos came from The origins of metallurgy: distinguishing stone from metal cut-marks on bones from archaeological sites .
I am amazed by the idea of &amp;ldquo;The origins of metallurgy: distinguishing stone from metal cut-marks on bones from archaeological sites&amp;rdquo;, which turns out to be an excellent demonstration of the usage of circumstantial evidence in the investigation of the origins of metalluurgy
In the discussion of origins of metalluurgy, our instinct is to find direct metal evidence.</description></item><item><title>Anth 207x: Why bipedality?</title><link>https://hellenshengfy.github.io/en/2023/04/10/anth-207x/</link><pubDate>Mon, 10 Apr 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://hellenshengfy.github.io/en/2023/04/10/anth-207x/</guid><description>I really like the edX course Anth 207x: Introduction to Human Evolution lectured by Professor Adam Van Arsdale of Wellesley College, and I took a series of notes to this course. This article is based on my notes.
Why we are bipedal creatures? There are various hypothesis:
Temperature: The environment in East African is hot and relatively dry, and it&amp;rsquo;s easier for a bipedal to stay cool during the day.</description></item><item><title>Anth 207x: Ardipithecus Model</title><link>https://hellenshengfy.github.io/en/2023/04/07/anth/</link><pubDate>Fri, 07 Apr 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://hellenshengfy.github.io/en/2023/04/07/anth/</guid><description>I really like the edX course Anth 207x: Introduction to Human Evolution lectured by Professor Adam Van Arsdale of Wellesley College, and I took a series of notes to this course. This article is based on my notes.
Ardipithecus is divided into two separate species based on dental and mandibular evidence:
Ardipithecus kadabba, dates back to about six million years ago
Ardipithecus ramidus, dates back to 4.</description></item><item><title>The earliest possible hominins: Orrorin tugenensis_osteology (7)</title><link>https://hellenshengfy.github.io/en/2023/04/05/osteology/</link><pubDate>Wed, 05 Apr 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://hellenshengfy.github.io/en/2023/04/05/osteology/</guid><description>As I find osteology extremely interesting, I decide to write a special series for osteology based on my notes of Anth 207x: Introduction to Human Evolution lectured by Professor Adam Van Arsdale of Wellesley College.
The fossile of Orrorin tugenensis was also discovered in 2001. They lived sometime 6 million years ago in Tugen Hills region, Rift Valley, Kenya.
The femur The most significant fossil of Orrorin tugenensis is a proximal femoral fragment becuase some features of this femur indicate that they might be bipedal.</description></item><item><title> Table: domestication of six domestic animals in China</title><link>https://hellenshengfy.github.io/en/2023/04/02/zoo/</link><pubDate>Sun, 02 Apr 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://hellenshengfy.github.io/en/2023/04/02/zoo/</guid><description>Animal Site Year Dog Nanzhuangtou 10000BP Pig Jiahu 9000BP Sheep Banpo 5600BP Cattle Cultural exchange through Hexi Corridor as early as 4500BP Horse Imported into China from the Eurasian steppe as early as 3000BP Chicken Cishan 8000BP Note that the archaeological evidence on the domestication of chicken in Cishan is still under debate now.</description></item><item><title>The earliest possible hominins: Sahelanthropus_osteology (6)</title><link>https://hellenshengfy.github.io/en/2023/03/29/osteology/</link><pubDate>Wed, 29 Mar 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://hellenshengfy.github.io/en/2023/03/29/osteology/</guid><description>As I find osteology extremely interesting, I decide to write a special series for osteology based on my notes of Anth 207x: Introduction to Human Evolution lectured by Professor Adam Van Arsdale of Wellesley College.
Discovered in 2001, Sahelanthropus was found in the desert of the Lake Chad basin in Central Africa.
Why we say that Sahelanthropus mgiht be a member of hominins? There are several osteological evidence to support this hypothesis :</description></item><item><title>The earliest possible hominins: summary table_osteology (5)</title><link>https://hellenshengfy.github.io/en/2023/03/27/osteology/</link><pubDate>Mon, 27 Mar 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://hellenshengfy.github.io/en/2023/03/27/osteology/</guid><description>As I find osteology extremely interesting, I decide to write a special series for osteology based on my notes of Anth 207x: Introduction to Human Evolution lectured by Professor Adam Van Arsdale of Wellesley College.
As we already know that chimps are not our ancestors, then who is? Any evidence of the earliest possible hominins?
Currently, there are three candidates we know:
Earliest possible hominins Name Place Date Sahelanthropus tchadensis Lake Chad Basin, Central Africa 6-7 mya Orrorin tugenensis Central Rift Valley, East Africa 6 mya Ardipithecus kadabba &amp;amp; ramidus Ethiopia &amp;amp; Kenya, East Africa 4-6 mya These candidates show somewhat reduced canine size and obligate or habitual bipedality.</description></item><item><title>How does bipedality influence our skeleton: tibia, pelvis and others_Osteology (4)</title><link>https://hellenshengfy.github.io/en/2023/03/20/osteology/</link><pubDate>Mon, 20 Mar 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://hellenshengfy.github.io/en/2023/03/20/osteology/</guid><description>As I find osteology extremely interesting, I decide to write a special series for osteology based on my notes of Anth 207x: Introduction to Human Evolution lectured by Professor Adam Van Arsdale of Wellesley College.
Less curved tibia Compared with the chimp&amp;rsquo;s tibia, human tibia is less curved and less flexed. This is because we human beings exclusively load our tibia from an anterior/posterior direction but chimps knuckwalk quadrupedally. Chimps do a lot of different activities where tibia get involved like climing the tree.</description></item><item><title>How does bipedality influence our skeleton: femur_Osteology (3)</title><link>https://hellenshengfy.github.io/en/2022/12/30/osteology/</link><pubDate>Fri, 30 Dec 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://hellenshengfy.github.io/en/2022/12/30/osteology/</guid><description>As I find osteology extremely interesting, I decide to write a special series for osteology based on my notes of Anth 207x: Introduction to Human Evolution lectured by Professor Adam Van Arsdale of Wellesley College.
Being bipedality is a tremendous shift. It involves changes of entire skeleton:
Femur: 1. Bicondylar angle Being bipedal means we walk on one leg for every step and this means great weight and pressure on our legs.</description></item><item><title>Anth 207x: Dating method</title><link>https://hellenshengfy.github.io/en/2022/12/26/dating-method/</link><pubDate>Mon, 26 Dec 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://hellenshengfy.github.io/en/2022/12/26/dating-method/</guid><description>I really like the edX course Anth 207x: Introduction to Human Evolution lectured by Professor Adam Van Arsdale of Wellesley College, and I took a series of notes to this course. This article is based on my notes.
Relative dating method 1.Geo-chronology: Correlate the age of different sedimentary layers across locations, particularly distinctive sedimentary layers like volcanic ash falls
2.Bio-chronolog: identify sequences based on fossils contained within these layers. For example, specific fossils are found across different locations.</description></item><item><title>How eating habit impacts skull_osteology (2)</title><link>https://hellenshengfy.github.io/en/2022/12/25/osteology/</link><pubDate>Sun, 25 Dec 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://hellenshengfy.github.io/en/2022/12/25/osteology/</guid><description>As I find osteology extremely interesting, I decide to write a special series for osteology based on my notes of Anth 207x: Introduction to Human Evolution lectured by Professor Adam Van Arsdale of Wellesley College.
I mentioned strong canine in primates in my last blog, so what a strong canine can lead to? Actually, it will exert great influence on the structure of canium.
Prominent snout. Roots of canines extend up into the rostrum resulting in more prominent snout on the skull.</description></item><item><title>Anth 207x: How to know when was the LCA?</title><link>https://hellenshengfy.github.io/en/2022/12/23/anth-207x/</link><pubDate>Fri, 23 Dec 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://hellenshengfy.github.io/en/2022/12/23/anth-207x/</guid><description>I really like the edX course Anth 207x: Introduction to Human Evolution lectured by Professor Adam Van Arsdale of Wellesley College, and I took a series of notes to this course. This article is based on my notes.
As we talked before that chimps and human being evolve from common ancestor, but who can we know when latest common ancestor (LCA) lived?
The answer lies in the molecular clock. In 1960s, geneticists found that differences in some protein structures were accumulating at a near constant rate through time, which made the time estimation of LCA possible.</description></item><item><title>Anth 207x: Miocene: the age of apes</title><link>https://hellenshengfy.github.io/en/2022/11/06/anth-207x/</link><pubDate>Sun, 06 Nov 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://hellenshengfy.github.io/en/2022/11/06/anth-207x/</guid><description>Miocene (a period between 22 million years ago and 5 million years ago) is sometimes known as &amp;ldquo;The Age of Apes&amp;rdquo;. A great diversity of apes lived on various continents of our planet during Miocene and the environment and the climate of the world was quite different from today.
During Miocene, the Mediterranean Sea used to be an open corridor of ocean during instead of a closed body of water. It thus connected the Atlantic Ocean and the Indian Ocean, allowing tropical forests to grow throughout Eurasia, not limited to tropical regions.</description></item><item><title>Eating habit: canine and honing complex_osteology (1)</title><link>https://hellenshengfy.github.io/en/2022/10/20/osteology/</link><pubDate>Thu, 20 Oct 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://hellenshengfy.github.io/en/2022/10/20/osteology/</guid><description>As I find osteology extremely interesting, I decide to write a special series for osteology based on my notes of Anth 207x: Introduction to Human Evolution lectured by Professor Adam Van Arsdale of Wellesley College.
In order to eat raw meat, apes developed strong canians together with a honing complex. Honing complex is a complex that (1) the lower canines project into the diastema between the upper canine and the lateral incisor and (2) the upper canine projects into the diastema between the lower canine and the lower third premolar.</description></item><item><title> CFA level II PASSED!</title><link>https://hellenshengfy.github.io/en/2022/10/11/cfa/</link><pubDate>Tue, 11 Oct 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://hellenshengfy.github.io/en/2022/10/11/cfa/</guid><description>After one year&amp;rsquo;s preparation, I finally claimed my CFA level II badge :-)</description></item><item><title>Anth 207x: Is evolution directional?</title><link>https://hellenshengfy.github.io/en/2022/09/03/anth-207xis-evolution-directional/</link><pubDate>Sat, 03 Sep 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://hellenshengfy.github.io/en/2022/09/03/anth-207xis-evolution-directional/</guid><description>I really like the edX course Anth 207x: Introduction to Human Evolution lectured by Professor Adam Van Arsdale of Wellesley College, and I took a series of notes to this course. This article is based on my notes.
My understanding of evolution: Lego though holes By definition, evolution is “the heritable changes in a population through time”. It seems like that evolution has a direction (for example: from simple to complex), but it is NOT the case.</description></item><item><title>Mount Tambora: the eruption that changed history</title><link>https://hellenshengfy.github.io/en/2022/05/15/tambora/</link><pubDate>Sun, 15 May 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://hellenshengfy.github.io/en/2022/05/15/tambora/</guid><description>The photo came from https://zhuanlan.zhihu.com/p/458646957
Mount Tambora erupted in 1815 with a VEI-7. The scale of it? Colossal! It reduced the global temperature by 0.7 degree Celsius in the coming year. This is an eruption that changed history.
Severe famine and social chaos in Europe because of crop failure
Mass migration to US during 1816-1821, which laid foundation for the development of US</description></item><item><title>Why is the P in BP set at 1950?</title><link>https://hellenshengfy.github.io/en/2022/03/28/anth/</link><pubDate>Mon, 28 Mar 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://hellenshengfy.github.io/en/2022/03/28/anth/</guid><description>I used to think that the reason to set the ‘present’ in BP at 1950 is because of the fact that 1950 is quite close to the discovery year of radiometric dating method.
That statement is a truth, but not the whole story. Here is the reason that is much more profound:
Nuclear bomb testing during the Cold War greatly disturbed the composition of the atmosphere and led to carbon-14 bomb pulse in 1963.</description></item><item><title>Documentary recommendation: Civilization</title><link>https://hellenshengfy.github.io/en/2022/01/13/second-post/</link><pubDate>Thu, 13 Jan 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://hellenshengfy.github.io/en/2022/01/13/second-post/</guid><description>YouTube Link: https://youtu.be/d2lJUOv0hLA</description></item><item><title>Machine learning, accounting and quantitive method_CFA notes</title><link>https://hellenshengfy.github.io/en/2021/11/08/second-post/</link><pubDate>Mon, 08 Nov 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://hellenshengfy.github.io/en/2021/11/08/second-post/</guid><description>Machine learning Accounting: IFRS GAAP comparison Quantitive method</description></item><item><title>Statistics: learn with Prof. Tang Liying</title><link>https://hellenshengfy.github.io/en/2021/08/15/second-post/</link><pubDate>Sun, 15 Aug 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://hellenshengfy.github.io/en/2021/08/15/second-post/</guid><description>This is the course lectured by prof. Tang Liying. I failed to find resources on Youtube, but you can view the class on Bilibili. Note that it is taught in Chinese.
Click the link below for more videos Part 1 : https://b23.tv/uRnzc3z Part 2 : https://b23.tv/10ynDXg</description></item><item><title>Misunderstandings: chimps are our ancestors/ our ancestors look like chimps</title><link>https://hellenshengfy.github.io/en/2021/05/19/misunderstandings/</link><pubDate>Wed, 19 May 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://hellenshengfy.github.io/en/2021/05/19/misunderstandings/</guid><description>Thanks to Darwin’s theory of evolution, now we know the fact that human beings are not created by god. However, many people hold the view that (1) chimps are our ancestors and (2) our ancestors look like chimps. These are misunderstandings.
Firstly, as what I wrote in my 2020-01-07 blog, Pan is the sister clay to Homos. Roughly 7 million years ago, chimps and human beings split from evolutionary tree and evolved in their own directions.</description></item><item><title>Y=AX:Essence of linear algebra</title><link>https://hellenshengfy.github.io/en/2021/05/13/second-post/</link><pubDate>Thu, 13 May 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://hellenshengfy.github.io/en/2021/05/13/second-post/</guid><description>I didn&amp;rsquo;t understand eigenvectors and eigenvalues until I watched 3Blue1Brown&amp;rsquo;s videos. I will recommend students to watch all his series.
YouTube Link: https://youtu.be/PFDu9oVAE-g</description></item><item><title> CFA level I badge claimed!</title><link>https://hellenshengfy.github.io/en/2021/04/21/cfa/</link><pubDate>Wed, 21 Apr 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://hellenshengfy.github.io/en/2021/04/21/cfa/</guid><description>I was busy preparing the test in the past three months and claimed my CFA level I badge :-)</description></item><item><title> Rt= In (Pt)-In (Pt-1) Auto-regression model: Blockchain (3)</title><link>https://hellenshengfy.github.io/en/2021/04/20/economy/</link><pubDate>Tue, 20 Apr 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://hellenshengfy.github.io/en/2021/04/20/economy/</guid><description>One of my colleagues asked me about my opinion on bitcoin, which reminded me of my graduation paper. Here is an excerpt from that paper. I used auto-regression model to prove the negative influence of bitcoin.
Negative Impacts of Blockchain Technology Application on Stock Market Operation System 3.1 Lack of Identity Verification At present, the traditional stock trading system consists of four segments: account opening, commissioning, transactions matching, and settlement and confirmation.</description></item><item><title> The Influences of Blockchain Technology Application on Stock Market Operation System (2)</title><link>https://hellenshengfy.github.io/en/2021/03/21/economy/</link><pubDate>Sun, 21 Mar 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://hellenshengfy.github.io/en/2021/03/21/economy/</guid><description>One of my colleagues asked me about my opinion on bitcoin, which reminded me of my graduation paper. Here is an excerpt from that paper, and I hope this could help you understand the postive influences of bitcoin.
Positive Impacts of Blockchain Technology Application on Stock Market Operation System 2.1 Primary Market: Self-verification and Confirmation of Stock Rights 2.1.1 Public Offering No matter what kind of listing system (approval system or registration system) a market applies, the priority of listing is to ensure that listed entities provide real financial information to the market so that investors can make right investment decisions.</description></item><item><title> The Influences of Blockchain Technology Application on Stock Market Operation System (1)</title><link>https://hellenshengfy.github.io/en/2021/03/17/economy/</link><pubDate>Wed, 17 Mar 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://hellenshengfy.github.io/en/2021/03/17/economy/</guid><description>One of my colleagues asked me about my opinion on bitcoin, which reminded me of my graduation paper. Here is an excerpt from that paper, and I hope this could help you understand what Bitcoin is and how it works.
Introduction of Blockchain Technology 1.1 Definition Technically, blockchain is a distributed database that maintains an ever-growing list of ordered records called blocks. Blocks are connected with each other by cryptography method.</description></item><item><title>A MIT course that saved my linear algebra</title><link>https://hellenshengfy.github.io/en/2021/02/16/second-post/</link><pubDate>Tue, 16 Feb 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://hellenshengfy.github.io/en/2021/02/16/second-post/</guid><description>This course helped me to get A in my final exam when I was an undergraduate student. Thank you Prof. Gilbert Strang!
YouTube Link: https://youtu.be/nHlE7EgJFds</description></item><item><title>Distinguish BP, BC, AD, BCE and CE</title><link>https://hellenshengfy.github.io/en/2021/02/01/book/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Feb 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://hellenshengfy.github.io/en/2021/02/01/book/</guid><description>What are the difference among BP,BC,AD,BCE and CE?
Chart below helps.
Photo credit to https://www.artobatours.com/articles/archaeology/bp-bc-bce-ad-ce-cal-mean/ AD: Anno Domini, i.e. &amp;ldquo;year of our Lord&amp;rdquo;, Christian era in the Gregorian calendar
BC: Before Christ, pre-Christian era in the Gregorian calendar.
CE: Common Era/Current Era, equivalent to AD, secular emphasis.
BCE: Before Common / Current Era.
BP: Before present (1950), date based on radiometric dating techniques.</description></item><item><title> Follow me on Hellentopia!</title><link>https://hellenshengfy.github.io/en/2021/01/01/cfa/</link><pubDate>Fri, 01 Jan 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://hellenshengfy.github.io/en/2021/01/01/cfa/</guid><description>I have a Chinese official account on wechat, in which I post a series of articles about history and art. Thanks for following me !
A screenshot of Hellentopia Wechat ID: gh_bf9142bca28c</description></item><item><title>!Please note that blogs before 2020 are archived!</title><link>https://hellenshengfy.github.io/en/2020/12/30/misunderstandings/</link><pubDate>Wed, 30 Dec 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://hellenshengfy.github.io/en/2020/12/30/misunderstandings/</guid><description>Content archived. Thanks for following my blogs!</description></item><item><title>Markdown Testing</title><link>https://hellenshengfy.github.io/en/2020/01/07/second-post/</link><pubDate>Tue, 07 Jan 2020 13:37:57 -0500</pubDate><guid>https://hellenshengfy.github.io/en/2020/01/07/second-post/</guid><description>See the source code of this page if you are interested.
H1 H2 H3 H4 H5 H6 List Water Water Water Water Water Water Water Water Water Water Water Water Table Water Water Water Water Water Water Water Water1 Water Water Water Water Quotes What I cannot create, I do not understand2.</description></item></channel></rss>