<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>English on Hugo-HT</title><link>https://hellenshengfy.github.io/tags/english/</link><description>Recent content in English on Hugo-HT</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Sun, 07 May 2023 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://hellenshengfy.github.io/tags/english/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Hominids, Hominioid, Hominines, Hominins: What’s the difference?</title><link>https://hellenshengfy.github.io/en/2023/05/07/second-post/</link><pubDate>Sun, 07 May 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://hellenshengfy.github.io/en/2023/05/07/second-post/</guid><description>Hominids, Hominioid, Hominines and Hominins? When I first come up with these terms, I was quite confused and found it hard to distinguish one from the other. After reading the paper Human Evolution: Taxonomy and Paleobiology, I decide to write this article and introduce you these terms under new taxonomic classification system which based on molecular evidence.
First of all, let me show you the chart, to make things easier. This chart is drawn based on the taxonomy table illustrated in Human Evolution: Taxonomy and Paleobiology.</description></item><item><title>On the birth of culture-historical archaeology</title><link>https://hellenshengfy.github.io/en/2023/04/27/essay-on-a-history-of-archaeological-thoughts/</link><pubDate>Thu, 27 Apr 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://hellenshengfy.github.io/en/2023/04/27/essay-on-a-history-of-archaeological-thoughts/</guid><description>The following is my essay for a class instructed by professor Yan Pan in Fudan University. The class is based on A History of Archaeological Thoughts by Bruce G.Trigger.
Hellen Sheng
Professor Yan Pan
A History of Archaeological Thoughts
April 27, 2023
On the birth of culture-historical archaeology The dramatic social transformation in the late nineteen centuries catalyzed the evolution and variation of archaeology ideology. Culture-historical archaeology became undoubtedly the most important method and theory among all.</description></item><item><title>My artifact drawings</title><link>https://hellenshengfy.github.io/en/2023/04/15/drawing/</link><pubDate>Sat, 15 Apr 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://hellenshengfy.github.io/en/2023/04/15/drawing/</guid><description>I audited artifact drawing class instructed by Ms.Dong Weimiao in Fudan University. Here are some of my sketches.
Geometric Shape Rostrum Classroom Human Skeleton Ceramic Cup</description></item><item><title>Anth 207x: Why bipedality?</title><link>https://hellenshengfy.github.io/en/2023/04/10/anth-207x/</link><pubDate>Mon, 10 Apr 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://hellenshengfy.github.io/en/2023/04/10/anth-207x/</guid><description>I really like the edX course Anth 207x: Introduction to Human Evolution lectured by Professor Adam Van Arsdale of Wellesley College, and I took a series of notes to this course. This article is based on my notes.
Why we are bipedal creatures? There are various hypothesis:
Temperature: The environment in East African is hot and relatively dry, and it&amp;rsquo;s easier for a bipedal to stay cool during the day.</description></item><item><title>Anth 207x: Ardipithecus Model</title><link>https://hellenshengfy.github.io/en/2023/04/07/anth/</link><pubDate>Fri, 07 Apr 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://hellenshengfy.github.io/en/2023/04/07/anth/</guid><description>I really like the edX course Anth 207x: Introduction to Human Evolution lectured by Professor Adam Van Arsdale of Wellesley College, and I took a series of notes to this course. This article is based on my notes.
Ardipithecus is divided into two separate species based on dental and mandibular evidence:
Ardipithecus kadabba, dates back to about six million years ago
Ardipithecus ramidus, dates back to 4.</description></item><item><title>The earliest possible hominins: Orrorin tugenensis_osteology (7)</title><link>https://hellenshengfy.github.io/en/2023/04/05/osteology/</link><pubDate>Wed, 05 Apr 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://hellenshengfy.github.io/en/2023/04/05/osteology/</guid><description>As I find osteology extremely interesting, I decide to write a special series for osteology based on my notes of Anth 207x: Introduction to Human Evolution lectured by Professor Adam Van Arsdale of Wellesley College.
The fossile of Orrorin tugenensis was also discovered in 2001. They lived sometime 6 million years ago in Tugen Hills region, Rift Valley, Kenya.
The femur The most significant fossil of Orrorin tugenensis is a proximal femoral fragment becuase some features of this femur indicate that they might be bipedal.</description></item><item><title>The earliest possible hominins: Sahelanthropus_osteology (6)</title><link>https://hellenshengfy.github.io/en/2023/03/29/osteology/</link><pubDate>Wed, 29 Mar 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://hellenshengfy.github.io/en/2023/03/29/osteology/</guid><description>As I find osteology extremely interesting, I decide to write a special series for osteology based on my notes of Anth 207x: Introduction to Human Evolution lectured by Professor Adam Van Arsdale of Wellesley College.
Discovered in 2001, Sahelanthropus was found in the desert of the Lake Chad basin in Central Africa.
Why we say that Sahelanthropus mgiht be a member of hominins? There are several osteological evidence to support this hypothesis :</description></item><item><title>The earliest possible hominins: summary table_osteology (5)</title><link>https://hellenshengfy.github.io/en/2023/03/27/osteology/</link><pubDate>Mon, 27 Mar 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://hellenshengfy.github.io/en/2023/03/27/osteology/</guid><description>As I find osteology extremely interesting, I decide to write a special series for osteology based on my notes of Anth 207x: Introduction to Human Evolution lectured by Professor Adam Van Arsdale of Wellesley College.
As we already know that chimps are not our ancestors, then who is? Any evidence of the earliest possible hominins?
Currently, there are three candidates we know:
Earliest possible hominins Name Place Date Sahelanthropus tchadensis Lake Chad Basin, Central Africa 6-7 mya Orrorin tugenensis Central Rift Valley, East Africa 6 mya Ardipithecus kadabba &amp;amp; ramidus Ethiopia &amp;amp; Kenya, East Africa 4-6 mya These candidates show somewhat reduced canine size and obligate or habitual bipedality.</description></item><item><title>How does bipedality influence our skeleton: tibia, pelvis and others_Osteology (4)</title><link>https://hellenshengfy.github.io/en/2023/03/20/osteology/</link><pubDate>Mon, 20 Mar 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://hellenshengfy.github.io/en/2023/03/20/osteology/</guid><description>As I find osteology extremely interesting, I decide to write a special series for osteology based on my notes of Anth 207x: Introduction to Human Evolution lectured by Professor Adam Van Arsdale of Wellesley College.
Less curved tibia Compared with the chimp&amp;rsquo;s tibia, human tibia is less curved and less flexed. This is because we human beings exclusively load our tibia from an anterior/posterior direction but chimps knuckwalk quadrupedally. Chimps do a lot of different activities where tibia get involved like climing the tree.</description></item><item><title>Anth 207x: Dating method</title><link>https://hellenshengfy.github.io/en/2023/03/15/dating-method/</link><pubDate>Wed, 15 Mar 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://hellenshengfy.github.io/en/2023/03/15/dating-method/</guid><description>I really like the edX course Anth 207x: Introduction to Human Evolution lectured by Professor Adam Van Arsdale of Wellesley College, and I took a series of notes to this course. This article is based on my notes.
Relative dating method 1.Geo-chronology: Correlate the age of different sedimentary layers across locations, particularly distinctive sedimentary layers like volcanic ash falls
2.Bio-chronolog: identify sequences based on fossils contained within these layers. For example, specific fossils are found across different locations.</description></item><item><title>How does bipedality influence our skeleton: femur_Osteology (3)</title><link>https://hellenshengfy.github.io/en/2023/01/20/osteology/</link><pubDate>Fri, 20 Jan 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://hellenshengfy.github.io/en/2023/01/20/osteology/</guid><description>As I find osteology extremely interesting, I decide to write a special series for osteology based on my notes of Anth 207x: Introduction to Human Evolution lectured by Professor Adam Van Arsdale of Wellesley College.
Being bipedality is a tremendous shift. It involves changes of entire skeleton:
Femur: 1. Bicondylar angle Being bipedal means we walk on one leg for every step and this means great weight and pressure on our legs.</description></item><item><title>How eating habit impacts skull_osteology (2)</title><link>https://hellenshengfy.github.io/en/2023/01/05/osteology/</link><pubDate>Thu, 05 Jan 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://hellenshengfy.github.io/en/2023/01/05/osteology/</guid><description>As I find osteology extremely interesting, I decide to write a special series for osteology based on my notes of Anth 207x: Introduction to Human Evolution lectured by Professor Adam Van Arsdale of Wellesley College.
I mentioned strong canine in primates in my last blog, so what a strong canine can lead to? Actually, it will exert great influence on the structure of canium.
Prominent snout. Roots of canines extend up into the rostrum resulting in more prominent snout on the skull.</description></item><item><title>Anth 207x: How to know when was the LCA?</title><link>https://hellenshengfy.github.io/en/2022/12/23/anth-207x/</link><pubDate>Fri, 23 Dec 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://hellenshengfy.github.io/en/2022/12/23/anth-207x/</guid><description>I really like the edX course Anth 207x: Introduction to Human Evolution lectured by Professor Adam Van Arsdale of Wellesley College, and I took a series of notes to this course. This article is based on my notes.
As we talked before that chimps and human being evolve from common ancestor, but who can we know when latest common ancestor (LCA) lived?
The answer lies in the molecular clock. In 1960s, geneticists found that differences in some protein structures were accumulating at a near constant rate through time, which made the time estimation of LCA possible.</description></item><item><title>Eating habit: canine and honing complex_osteology (1)</title><link>https://hellenshengfy.github.io/en/2022/12/20/osteology/</link><pubDate>Tue, 20 Dec 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://hellenshengfy.github.io/en/2022/12/20/osteology/</guid><description>As I find osteology extremely interesting, I decide to write a special series for osteology based on my notes of Anth 207x: Introduction to Human Evolution lectured by Professor Adam Van Arsdale of Wellesley College.
In order to eat raw meat, apes developed strong canians together with a honing complex. Honing complex is a complex that (1) the lower canines project into the diastema between the upper canine and the lateral incisor and (2) the upper canine projects into the diastema between the lower canine and the lower third premolar.</description></item><item><title>Anth 207x: Miocene: the age of apes</title><link>https://hellenshengfy.github.io/en/2022/11/06/anth-207x/</link><pubDate>Sun, 06 Nov 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://hellenshengfy.github.io/en/2022/11/06/anth-207x/</guid><description>Miocene (a period between 22 million years ago and 5 million years ago) is sometimes known as &amp;ldquo;The Age of Apes&amp;rdquo;. A great diversity of apes lived on various continents of our planet during Miocene and the environment and the climate of the world was quite different from today.
During Miocene, the Mediterranean Sea used to be an open corridor of ocean during instead of a closed body of water. It thus connected the Atlantic Ocean and the Indian Ocean, allowing tropical forests to grow throughout Eurasia, not limited to tropical regions.</description></item><item><title>Anth 207x: Is evolution directional?</title><link>https://hellenshengfy.github.io/en/2022/11/03/anth-207xis-evolution-directional/</link><pubDate>Thu, 03 Nov 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://hellenshengfy.github.io/en/2022/11/03/anth-207xis-evolution-directional/</guid><description>I really like the edX course Anth 207x: Introduction to Human Evolution lectured by Professor Adam Van Arsdale of Wellesley College, and I took a series of notes to this course. This article is based on my notes.
My understanding of evolution: Lego though holes By definition, evolution is “the heritable changes in a population through time”. It seems like that evolution has a direction (for example: from simple to complex), but it is NOT the case.</description></item><item><title>Misunderstandings: chimps are our ancestors/ our ancestors look like chimps</title><link>https://hellenshengfy.github.io/en/2021/05/19/misunderstandings/</link><pubDate>Wed, 19 May 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://hellenshengfy.github.io/en/2021/05/19/misunderstandings/</guid><description>Thanks to Darwin’s theory of evolution, now we know the fact that human beings are not created by god. However, many people hold the view that (1) chimps are our ancestors and (2) our ancestors look like chimps. These are misunderstandings.
Firstly, as what I wrote in my 2020-01-07 blog, Pan is the sister clay to Homos. Roughly 7 million years ago, chimps and human beings split from evolutionary tree and evolved in their own directions.</description></item><item><title>Markdown Testing</title><link>https://hellenshengfy.github.io/en/2021/01/07/second-post/</link><pubDate>Thu, 07 Jan 2021 13:37:57 -0500</pubDate><guid>https://hellenshengfy.github.io/en/2021/01/07/second-post/</guid><description>See the source code of this page if you are interested.
H1 H2 H3 H4 H5 H6 List Water Water Water Water Water Water Water Water Water Water Water Water Table Water Water Water Water Water Water Water Water1 Water Water Water Water Quotes What I cannot create, I do not understand2.</description></item><item><title>!Please note that blogs before 2020 are archived!</title><link>https://hellenshengfy.github.io/en/2020/12/30/misunderstandings/</link><pubDate>Wed, 30 Dec 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://hellenshengfy.github.io/en/2020/12/30/misunderstandings/</guid><description>Content archived. Thanks for following my blogs!</description></item></channel></rss>